<chapter id="chapter-welcome">
  <title>Welcome!</title>

  <!-- This is at the top level to avoid any chapter TOC. -->

  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">Geotools</emphasis>
    is a Java language code library which provides the classes, 
    objects, and methods required to implement standards conformant geospatial 
    applications. Geotools can be used to build applications of many different 
    types covering most processes of geographic information systems including 
    network server applications and desktop clients. The library consists of 
    various modules which can be combined according to programmer needs. An 
    example client application is included as the &geot; demo shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-geotools-demo-render" /> .
    <!-- SYNC WITH QUICKSTART-RUNTHEDEMO -->
    <figure id="fig-geotools-demo-render">
      <title>The Geotools Demo showing an unprojected map of the world.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/geotools-demo-render.png" 
                        format="PNG" 
                        width="600px"
                        scalefit="1"
                        />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>
              A screenshot of the user demo.
            </phrase>
          </textobject>
          <caption>
            <para>
              The &geot; demonstration application uses swing components, such 
              as a label, buttons, and a text area, but also uses the JMapPane
              component to display geospatial data and provide a simple toolbar 
              with tools to manipulate those data.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    Geotools, in the 2.x series of releases, currently uses version 1.4 of the 
    Java language and therefore does not include generics or other recent 
    developments of the Java language. The Geotools project
    <ulink url="http://www.geotools.org/" type="http">webpage</ulink> contains 
    extensive information about the project and the library including project 
    news, links to code downloads, and documentation.
  </para>
    
  <warning>
    <title>Geotools is a library <emphasis>not</emphasis> an application.</title>
    <para>
      Geotools provides almost no graphical user interface functionality. Several 
      efforts may yield more user interface elements, notably the GO-1 module in 
      the gt/ext/go directory and the 
      <ulink url="http://geowidgets.sourceforge.net/" type="http">
        GeoWidgets project
      </ulink> which will hopefully provide widgets based on the 
      <ulink url="http://geoapi.sourceforge.net/" type="http">
        GeoAPI
      </ulink> interfaces. 
    </para>

    <para>
      There are two notable projects which leverage Geotools to provide 
      higher level functionality:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <ulink url="http://www.geoserver.org/" type="http">
              Geoserver
            </ulink> is a network server to provide maps using the Web 
            Mapping Standard (WMS) or to provide individual features using the 
            Web Feature Standard (WFS) and its transactional extension, the Web 
            Feature Standard for Transactions (WFS-T).  
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <ulink url="http://udig.refractions.net/" type="http">
              User-friendly Desktop Internet GIS (uDig)
            </ulink> is both a powerful desktop application and a platform for 
            the creation of other applications. The platform draws on the  
            <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/" type="http">
              Eclipse
            </ulink> project and its 
            <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/rcp/" type="http">
              Rich Client Plarform 
            </ulink> sub-project.   
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      There are also many other software projects for 
      spatial data which may be easier to use for simple projects than the 
      Geotools library. For example, the 
      <ulink url="http://www.jump-project.org/" type="http">
        JUMP
      </ulink> project and its 
      <ulink url="http://openjump.org/" type="http">
        OpenJUMP
      </ulink> fork are reputedly easy to use. The 
      <ulink url="http://www.freegis.org/" type="http">
        FreeGIS
      </ulink> project attempts to maintain a list of the free software 
      projects related to geospatial data. Those projects, or others like 
      them, may be a better place to start than working directly with the
      library itself.
    </para>
  </warning>
  
  
  
  
  <!-- The Users' Manual -->
  <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">The Geotools Users' Manual</emphasis> documents the 
    design of the library, explains the use of each modular subsystem, and 
    provides background to the tutorials distributed with the source code itself 
    in order to help programers develop new geospatial applications using part 
    or all of the Geotools library. This manual should help users get started 
    using the Geotools library, we hope to the point that users can continue on
    their own by reading the GeoAPI and Geotools javadocs along with the source 
    code. Advanced questions should be addressed to the mailing list or 
    raised in the Internet Relay Chat (IRC) room as explained on the project 
    webpage.
  </para>

  <note>
    <title>The Users' Manual vs the Developers' Guide</title>
    <para>
      The Users' Manual is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a guide to developing and 
      improving the &geot; library itself.
    </para>
    <para> 
      The Developers' Guide provides helpful information for those who want to
      contribute to the library itself. For more information, see the 
      <ulink url="http://www.geotools.org/Develop/" type="http">developers page
      </ulink> of the web site.
    </para>
  </note>

</chapter>





