<!-- Top Level, a description with the chapter TOC -->

    <para>
      This chapter describes, first, how to obtain the library and the 
      tools required to be able to use the Geotools library and, second, 
      how to use these libraries to display a map on screen with an 
      exceedingly primitive application. 
    </para>

    <para>
      The chapter assumes that the programmer understands the following:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          The Java (tm) Programming Language
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The basics of Geographic Information Systems 
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      This chapter tries not to assume any other specialized knowledge; 
      the examples therefore start from the basic desktop of modern GUI 
      operating systems either of the UNIX heritage, namely GNU based or 
      MacOS X, or from the CPM heritage, namely Windows (tm). Since each
      programmer uses her own tools to actually develop her programs, each 
      will have to adapt these examples to fit her own needs.
    </para>

<sect1 id="sect-quick-start-getGt">
    <title>Get Geotools</title>

    <para>
      Geotools is distributed in three separate pieces: as a binary 
      distribution, as a source distribution, and as a javadoc collection. 
      Each of these can be obtained from the project website.
    </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="sect-quick-start-configJava">
    <title>Configure Java</title>

    <para>
      Geotools requires a Java VM and two imaging libraries, the 
      Java Advanced Imaging library and the Java Image I/O library. These 
      must all be configured correctly for the examples which follow.
    </para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="sect-quick-start-runDemo">
    <title>Run the Demo</title>

    <para>
      Geotools contains a handy demonstration application which is useful
      both to ensure that the libraries are properly installed and to get 
      programmers started exploring each of the different areas of the 
      library.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once the Java libraries have been configured, a simple demonstration
      program can be run with the following command:
    </para>

    <para>
      <computeroutput>
java -jar /path/to/gt2-demo-introduction-VERSION_NUMBER.jar org.geotools.demo.introduction.QuickStartGUI
      </computeroutput>
    </para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="sect-quick-start-readDeom">
    <title>Read the Demo</title>

    <para>
      The source code for the Demo application provides a quick introduction 
      to each of the major modules of the code library. The source walks 
      through the process of creating Features, both programatically and from 
      various sources such as shapefile and web servers. The source then
      discusses how to create styles and display a map. The source continues 
      by discussing advanced features of the &lib; library. The source is 
      contained in the
      <filename>org.geotools.demo.introduction.QuickStartGUI.java</filename>
      source file within the 
      <filename>gt2-demo-introduction-VERSION.jar</filename>
      JAR file (where VERSION is replaced by the current version number).
    </para>

</sect1>









