<!-- 
  This is at the top level to avoid any chapter TOC.
-->

<para>
  Geotools is a code library for Geospatial applications. The 
  library is intended to provide foundational object classes for 
  creating geographic information systems. The library is 
  written in the Java computer language, currently using 
  version &javaVersion;. For more details, visit the Geotools project 
  <ulink url="http://www.geotools.org/" type="http">webpage</ulink>.
</para>


<para>
  This manual intends to help people develop software programs which use part
  or all of the Geotools library to create their own geospatial applications. 
  These programmers are considered <emphasis>users</emphasis> of the &lib; 
  library.
  This manual is intended to help programers learn how to use both the 
  GeoTools library itself and closely related libraries such as the GeoAPI 
  and JTS libraries. 
</para>

<para>
  &lib; can be used to build applications of many different types including 
  network server applications and desktop clients. The library consists of 
  various modules which can be combined according to programmer needs. An 
  example client application is included as the &lib; demo shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-geotools-demo" /> .
    <figure id="fig-geotools-demo">
      <title>The Geotools Demo showing an unprojected map of the world.</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/geotools-demo.png" 
                     format="PNG" 
                     width="600px"
                     scalefit="1"
                     />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>
            A screenshot of the user demo.
          </phrase>
        </textobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The &lib; demonstration application uses swing components, such 
            as a label, buttons, and a text area, but also uses the JMapPane
            component to display geospatial data and provide a simple toolbar 
            with tools to manipulate those data.
	  </para>
	</caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
    This manual will get users started using the geotools codebase. We hope
    the manual can get users to the point that they can continue on their 
    own by reading the GeoAPI and Geotools javadocs along with the source 
    code. Advanced questions should be addressed to the mailing list or 
    raised in the Internet Relay Chat (IRC) room.
  </para>

<warning>
  <para>
    This manual is not a guide to developing and improving the library itself; 
    for that see the 
    <ulink url="http://www.geotools.org/Develop/" type="http">developers page
    </ulink> of the web site and the Developers' Guide available from that web
    page.
  </para>
</warning>

<warning>
  <para>
    Geotools is explicitly <emphasis>not</emphasis> an extensible application. Geotools provides almost no graphical user interface functionality. Several projects may yield more user interface elements, notably the 
    <ulink url="http://geowidgets.sourceforge.net/" type="http">
      GeoWidgets project
    </ulink> which will hopefully provide widgets based on the 
    <ulink url="http://geoapi.sourceforge.net/" type="http">
      GeoAPI
    </ulink> interfaces. 
  </para>

  <para>
    There are two notable projects which leverage Geotools to provide 
    higher level functionality. 
  </para>

  <para>
    The 
    <ulink url="http://www.geoserver.org/" type="http">
      Geoserver
    </ulink> project is a network server to provide maps using the Web 
    Mapping Standard (WMS) or to provide individual features using the 
    Web Feature Standard (WFS) and its transactional extension, the Web 
    Feature Standard for Transactions (WFS-T).  
  </para>

  <para>
    The 
    <ulink url="http://udig.refractions.net/" type="http">
      User-friendly Desktop Internet GIS (uDig)
    </ulink> project provides a powerful platform for the creation of 
    user, desktop-based applications drawing on the  
    <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/" type="http">
      Eclipse
    </ulink> project and its 
    <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/rcp/" type="http">
      Rich Client Plarform 
    </ulink> sub-project.   
  </para>

  <para>
    There are also many other software projects for 
    spatial data which may be easier to use for simple projects than the 
    Geotools library. For example, the 
    <ulink url="http://www.jump-project.org/" type="http">
      JUMP
    </ulink> project and its 
    <ulink url="http://openjump.org/" type="http">
      OpenJUMP
    </ulink> fork are reputedly easy to use. The 
    <ulink url="http://www.freegis.org/" type="http">
      FreeGIS
    </ulink> project attempts to maintain a list of the free software 
    projects related to geospatial data. Those projects, or others like 
    them, may be a better place to start than working directly with the
    library itself.
  </para>
</warning>





